let's continue from where we left the last time we spoke about present value in the last example
or the last video let's do a quick revision of one more example around present value and then
move forward let's say the second case where the investment that the client please figure out the
investment that the client would have to make either client desires 25 lakh rupees after 20 years
for daughters marriage so basically you end up meeting a client client says I want 25 lakh rupees
after 20 years and the return that you are discussing is roughly 10% then how much
amount of money should the client invest today as well so so what we have is this where we are
saying that the client needs 25 lakh rupees after 20 years and the return we are discussing is 10%
we have to help the client understand that if it does not want to do a lot
SIP but a lump sum how much money would the client be required to invest together so this is our rate
this is our empire and this is our future then we have to find the present value what do we do
same thing go to excel so we go to excel go to effects in effects in the search bar we write
pv because that's what we want to find double click your rate is 10%
n per is 20 yeah n per is 20 rate 25 we don't know what PMT is let's leave it empty our future value is
25 lakhs 1 2 3 4 5 we don't know what typies we leave that empty click enter
3 lakhs 71,609 3 lakhs 71,609 minus so we are saying if the client is investing 3 lakhs 71,609
today and if the fund is able to generate 10% for 20 years then the client will have 25 lakhs for
daughter's marriage one important thing that we could have discussed in the last video was why
does this show minus in present value the answer is very simple because you are going to invest
this money and it is going to go out of your pocket so whenever it goes out of your pocket it is
minus like we learned the last time which is why this is showing you as minus let's move ahead then
now we are saying let's say if your client is investing 10 lakhs today and the rate the client is
expecting is 15% then what is the maturity value will the client get after 10 years again very
appropriate question from the client a lot of them ask us if I invest 10 lakhs how much will I get
after 10 years let's try and figure that out so this question is where the client is saying what if
I invest 10 lakhs today I am writing that as minus because he is going to invest and it is going
to go out of his pocket how much will I get after 10 years if the return is 15% is what the client
is wanting to know so we have our present value 10 lakhs is invested today we have our rate
we have our emperor we have to figure out the future value and help the client understand
if this turns out to be true how much will the client get at the end of the 10th year so we are going to
excel right now what do we want to find we want to find future value this time so we will click on
fx and in the search we will write f we we wrote pv in the last case because we wanted to find pv now
we are writing fv because we want to find the future value so we write fv we find fv here double click
again a window pops up very similar now here what's our rate we are saying our rate is 15% so we write
15 what's our emperor so we are saying our emperor is 10 pmt we don't know we'll leave that empty
pv yes I know minus 10 lakhs 1 2 3 4 5 minus it is going out of my pocket type I don't know I'll leave
it empty so I had three information I input all the three information I click and up
here is where I get my future value 40 lakhs 45000 557 40 lakhs 45000 557 which means if the client is
investing 10 lakhs today and if it grows at 15% for 10 years the client can expect 40 lakh 45000
right this is how it is going to help you solve any given situation while you are in front of the
client with simple basic excel and strength right let's move forward now suppose if the client wants
to do one lakh of SIP every year which grows at 10% what will be the maturity value after 25 years
so now this question is client is not doing one time investment client is investing one lakh each year
one lakh I'm writing minus is because it is going to go out of the client's pocket for how long
25 years for 25 years and if the return is let's say 10% we have to figure out the maturity value
let's say return is 10% we have to figure out the maturity value now we know this is n per
we know this is rate we know we have to find the maturity value so we have to find the future value
then what is this now this is a new element that we have to understand now okay is this lump sum
no because I'm not doing it one time I'm doing it multiple times in our case I'm doing it every year
for 25 years right so whenever you have a cash flow this is called a cash flow you're doing it
year after year year after year or you can do it month after month whenever you have a cash flow
which is constant and the value is same you call that cash flow as PMP or you call it payment
which is the full form of the abbreviation PMP so understand what was PV lump sum what was FV lump sum
but while you're trying to do investment you don't always invest as lump sum right you can invest in
parts also like say SIP so SIP can't be called present value because it doesn't happen today it
does not happen once it happens repeatedly so whenever you have a cash flow right which is constant
and same example SIP or EMI they will always be constant 5000 every month right so every month
is constant amount is the same right that's the same case with EMI it'll always be the same amount
in every month so the time between two cash flows is constant every month and the amount is also
constant such a cash flow where between two cash flows the time is same every month or every quarter
every semi annual every year when this time is constant of the repetitiveness and the amount is
constant 5 lakh 10 lakhs 5,000 10,000 you call that cash flow as a payment which means whenever
you get an SIP or EMI or an annuity that you and I will discuss we will use that as PMP because it's
a cash flow which has which has constant period between two cash flows in this example every year
constant it happens every year right so every year is constant you can be every month constant
every quarter constant and the amount is also same 1 lakh 1 lakh 1 lakh we will call this cash flow
as payment payment so very quickly what is this question this question is 1 lakh as SIP at 10% for 25
years so 1 lakh minus 1 lakh every year for 25 years at 10% find the maturity value so I have the
period correct I have the rate and I have this new element which I call as PMP what do I have to find
future value right how do we find that same go to excel now here I want to find payment I will go to
effects in the search bar I will write PMP years PMP I will double click it same window will open up
and I will input the data like we've been doing for the last four examples what's the rate the rate
in our case is 10% register yeah 10% right what's our info our info is 25 so 25 what's our PV we don't
have a PV because there is no lump sum investment that has happened right so our PV because it is not
given we will keep that blank right not given so blank sorry my bad we got this wrong we actually
didn't have to find the PMT we already have the PMT we have to find the future my bad right so we
will go to effects in the search bar we will write FV we click FV what's our rate 10% what's our
info 25 check here 25 when 10% what's our payment payment is given to us how much minus 1 lakh I'm
doing minus or minus it is going out of my pocket 1 lakh is the yearly SIP PV I don't have the PV
there is no one time lump sum investment that has happened so I'll keep it blank type I've not yet
learned so I'm going to keep that blank right I click enter how much do I get 98 lakh 34 705 98
lakh 35 705 so if the client is investing a lack of rupee every year for 25 years and the return is
10% the client will have at maturity roughly 98 lakh 35 705 I hope this is absolutely clear now
like we understood PMT in this example I'm going to introduce something new for 20 which you saw
over the last four examples now say for example in the same case above there can be two cases right
case one and case two case one I'm investing one lakh rupee every year but this investment is
happening on the Jan of the year so let's say Jan 20 another one like goes on Jan 21 another one
like goes on Jan 22 and the maturity is December 29 or let's say December 50 right case two
case two okay let's stick to what the question is so let's say December 45 so I will do 1 lakh
each year I will do 1 lakh each year for 25 years maturity is December 45
case two I'm doing 1 lakh each year for 25 years but my investment happens in at the end of the year
December 20 another 1 lakh will happen in December 21 then December 22 and the maturity is December
25 now if you carefully observe PMT here is 1 lakh period here is 25 period here is 25
right and the return also assume is the same which is let's say 8% sorry in our case it is 10%
so let's say 10% 10% here and if you observe here it's exactly the same thing what's your PMT
1 lakh PMT is 1 lakh here right you are doing investments for 25 years and the return here also
is 10% now if both the data are same where we are saying in both the cases here also in this entire
case I am doing 25 investments of 1 lakh rupees and here also I'm doing 25 investments of 1 lakh
rupees here also the return is 10% here also the return is 10% are we trying to say that both at the
end of the year 25 years we'll end up giving the same return the answer is why because over here
you invested in Jan and hence your investment is going to be invested for one more year versus
this investment because over here you invested in December and the maturity is same so here I'm
going to make returns more for one full year right is because here I'm investing at the beginning of
the month rather the year and year I'm investing at the end of the year and hence though the data
mathematically look the same PMT 1 lakh N per 25 and rate 10% the answer in both the cases should come
different this in excel is given as type so this is type 1 and this is type 2 type 0 so whenever the
investor is investing the cash flow at the beginning of the year or beginning of the month we will write
the type as 1 whenever the investor is investing the cash flow at the end of the month or end of the year
we will write the type as 0 now this is only applicable when it is cash flow right like you saw while we
were doing the earlier three four questions we didn't have PMT neither we were asked to find PMT
nor did we have PMT in the question right which is why we did not bother about the type course
type will only come into picture while you are either trying to find the SIP value or you are investing
in SIP because it is exactly where you have to tell the computer whether I'm doing the investment
at the beginning of the year or the month or at the end of the year or woman is where type is extremely
important and I will show you how the answer changes let's say if the client was investing at
the beginning of the month this is beginning of the year this example let's say gen 20 then what was
the return that the client would have made all I would have had to do is just write the type as 1
when I write the type as 1 I am telling the computer that the investment of one lakh for 25 years is
happening at the beginning of the year now because I'm going to get one full entire year that I
explained to you here right see my answer change to 1 crore it lacks but if I am doing the same
investment if I'm doing the same investment at the end right I will keep the type as 0 or even if I
leave it blank it means 0 because I'm getting one year less look at my future value which is 98 lakhs
so the point that I'm trying to make here is type comes into picture while you have either
payment or cash flow given to you or you are supposed to find either you are doing an SIP or you are
supposed to find how much SIP do I have to do is where type comes into picture and it is very
important that you mention 1 or 0 right is because 1 or 0 is when the computer will understand
that whether the cash flow is happening at the beginning of the period or at the end of the period
now georotically in financial planning you always want to make sure that your type is 1 right I'm not
editing this is because financial planning what you intend to do is let's say on the first you get
5 lakh rupees a salary you want to invite a habit in your client that sir first you invest
and whatever amount of money is left is what you then go ahead and spend you don't want to be in a
situation where the client spends the entire month and then invest whatever is remaining at the end
which is why why we are trying to do financial planning we will always try and keep our type as 1
is because we want to invite the culture of investing at the beginning of the period and not at the
end of the period I hope this is absolutely clear and I'm going to take you a step forward let's say
now the client is telling us that I'm going to invest a lack of rupees for 25 years and the return
we will make is 10 percent but this one lack I'm not going to invest every year but every month
now tell me how much do I get at maturity at the end of the 25th year how is this question different
from the last question that we did everything is the same except that 1 lakh is instead of year which
was the last case happening every month in this case that we are discussing about how is this question
let's try and figure out so what is a period here in per or our period is 25 years
what's our rate we're saying our rate is 10 percent per year we are saying what's our PMT
we're saying a PMT is 1 lakh rupees every month what do we have to find future value
right now the only strange thing here is while both of these are given in years this is given in
months now we've been learning this is school level mathematics that you know generally when you are
given multiply 1 1 liter with 25 milliliters either you're trying to convert everything in
milliliters and then multiply or you try and convert everything in liter and then multiply
correct you cannot ideally go ahead and multiply generally 1 liter with 250 milliliters you
try and make sure that either everything is in milliliters or everything is in liters right that's
exactly the challenger we have two components which are in years we have one component which is in
months which is why there is one more step that we have to do before we move on to the actual excel
calculation what is that convert either everything in two months or everything into years and then figure
out what we want to do now generally a lot of us are lazy and we'll say because we already have
two things in years why not multiply this by 12 and convert this into year no does not work do you
really think investing a lack of rupee in Jan then investing a lack of rupee in February so on and so
forth for 12 months is equivalent to investing 12 lakh rupees together either at the start of the year
or end of the year absolutely not does not make sense so always remember you cannot add multiply
subtract divide PMT add on PMT has to stay in the form it is in so in our case PMT is in months PMT
is in months you will have to convert everything else into months as simple as that so simple in whichever
form you have PMT you will convert everything else in that form so PMT is in months I will convert
everything else into months now how do I convert everything else into months 25 years is how many
months so I'm saying 25 years is 300 months now I'm saying 10% per year is how many how much per month
so I will say 10% divide by 8.82 per month now a disclaimer here 0.82 is georotically for
almost CFP or CFA exam perspective not the right answer the right answer may be 0.8 now I'm not going
into too much of detailing is because here we are not trying to prepare for an exam we are trying to
understand logic so we will stick to 0.82 here right so we are saying 1000 per month we are saying 0.82
per month we are saying 300 per month everything's become month and now I can go ahead and find the answer
right so I'm saying if I invest one lakh every month 10% is the rate for 25 years how much will the
client get at much or it so I want to find the future value so in the search I already have future
value returns I will click what's the rate my rate is 10% divided by 12 now you can do it here only
you don't have to do a separate calculation elsewhere 10% divided by 12 see it has already calculated
0.83 and per my input is 25 into 12 see 300 you already calculated what's my PMT minus one lakh
am I doing any lump sum investment right now together no so I leave a PVS blank now because we just
understood I want to make sure that the investments are happening at the beginning so I will do the
calculation as type 1 enter here is what your answer is the client is investing a lack of rupee
every month for 25 years and the return is 10% then the client will have 13 crore 37 lakhs 89,000
maturity 13.37 crore at maturity I hope this is absolutely clearly understood
you know why type 1 is different from type 0 why type 1 is beginning type 0 is end why do we use
type 1 generally you understood PMT you understood how is PMT every year different from PMT every month
how you understood how PMT cannot be multiplied by 12 and you will have to convert everything else
in the format in which PMT is right and this is how you do a calculation so now we've understood
everything that was there on the excel if you see we've understood what is PV we've understood
what is FV we've understood what is PMT we've understood what is end per we've understood what is
rate and we've also understood what is time right let's solve one or two questions more
so that your basic becomes absolutely clear around this before we move ahead so let's say
what is the monthly SIP you will recommend to your client if you want 50 lakh rupees at retirement
which is after 30 years and the rate is 11% so now the question is that my client wants 50 lakh rupees
at retirement after 30 years these are random numbers and the values can be anything return is 11%
this is a very valid question tell me the SIP I will have to do to make sure I get 50 lakhs
so what all is given to me future value is given I have 30 lakhs my end per is given
right and my rate is given so let me write that down so I have end per given to me as 30 years
I have rate given to me as 11% per year I have future value given to me as 50 lakhs
and I have to figure out PMT SIP so I have to figure out PMT how much do I have to invest every month
now you know that you need the answer per month correct so you will have to input data per month
but both of these are per year so how do I convert I will divide by 12 or multiply by 12 and divide
I am repeating again this divide by 12 may theoretically be slightly different than what I am trying to show
you but don't worry your answer will more or less come this way so now I am saying now I want to
find the SIP amount I want to find the PMT so I will go to the search bar I will write PMT
here is where the PMT is and double click so what is my rate I will say my rate is 11%
divide by 12 because I want the answer in months so I am converting n per and rate into months
right 11% divide by 12 what is my n per I am saying 30 into 12
30 into 12 pv am I investing something lump sum together the answer is no so I leave it blank
future how much do I want in the future 50 lakhs 50 1 2 3 4 5 and I am talking about type 1 because
I want to do my SIP at the beginning of the months or type 1 inter I will only have to do an SIP of 1766
66 every month for 30 years I will get 50 lakh rupees every year I hope this is absolutely
clearly understood by each one of you and there are no doubts around any of these things
that we have discussed quickly we have a couple of more questions let's all them what return has
the client generated now this might help because client would have invested somewhere else and you
want to help the client and understand especially in insurance that the client is actually not making
any money that's it so what return as a client generated if he invested 1 lakh 50 thousand each
year and received 13 lakhs after 7 years so I am saying if the client invested 1 lakh 50 thousand
each year so it's a cash flow so PMD and after 7 years received 13 lakhs find the return that
the client has generated now this is our future value this is our NPR and this is our PMD right
we have to find what the rate that the client managed to earn on the investment so we will go to excel
now I will search for rate RPE here's the rate I will double click the same window will open up what's
my NPR my NPR is 7 so I will write 7 what's my PMD how much did I invest each year 1 and a half
lakh minus 1 and a half lakh going out of my pocket PV I did no lump sum investment so I leave PV
blank how much did I receive in the future future value 13 lakhs 13 1 2 3 4 5 type again we don't
know the type but because we are assuming this is insurance sorry because we are assuming this is
insurance right type is always 1 because in insurance premium is taken in advance at the beginning
so while you are trying to do any insurance question make sure your type is always beginning
because in insurance investments are taken at the beginning right so I wrote type as 1 and I click
enter I will just expand this a little so that I get clarity so if the client has invested 1 and a
half lakh rupees for 7 years and received 13 lakhs at maturity the client has actually only managed
to get 5.34% of votes I hope this is absolutely clear and there are no doubts around understanding
any of these things last question calculate the annual interest rate in percentage required
if the client is investing 15,000 today and expects to receive 25,000 in 12 years time so let's say you
end up meeting a client who is telling you that you know I only have 15,000 rupees to present value
and I want 25,000 rupees at the end of the 12th year tell me the return that I need see because
only if you know the return you will be able to help the client which asset class should he
she invested right so we are saying client is investing 15 present value client needs 25
future value after 12 years find the return that the client should generate simple go to excel search
for it what's our end per after how many years 12 years PMT is there a cash flow no I will leave
it blank present value yes client is willing to invest 15,000 today so minus 15,000
future value yes the client is looking at getting 25,000 these are random numbers you can
put in any number you want type because there is no PMT here neither given or asked type doesn't
matter I can write one zero my answer would change so all the data that was given to me I have written
I'll just click enter I'll get the answer I'll just expand this so the client only needs to generate
4.35% return if the client has 15,000 and the client expects to receive 25,000 right so if somebody
is invested in an insurance 15,000 rupees today and after 12 years rupees receives 25,000 the client
has ideally made only 4.35% returns I hope through this all of these things of basic how to find
return how to find a present value future value how to find SIP value is all absolutely clearly
understood to each one of you all now that these basic calculations are clear I will take you to
study and help you understand how to do goal based plan thank you see you in the next study